Guide to the Sol Gorelick Papers WAG.019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Sol Gorelick Papers
Bulk, 1960-1980
circa 1940-1980
WAG.019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
17.25 linear feet in 17 record cartons and 1 manuscript box.
Sol Gorelick (1916-2004) was a social worker and union activist. He began his career with the City of New York in 1940 as a caseworker at the Brownsville Welfare Center. He would work with the city's welfare departments in Brooklyn until his retirement in 1980, also working at the Boro Hall Center and Fulton Center. The range of city documents maintained by Gorelick include memorandums, correspondence, procedural manuals, and educational materials. They document the city's bureaucratic culture, labor relations, unemployment, social conditions, health and healthcare, and housing in mid-20th century Brooklyn. Gorelick was a union member throughout his career with the city. His longest membership was with the Welfare Local 371 of AFSCME, District Council 37. He was a member during the union's tempestuous 1960s, which saw tense contract standoffs with the city, strikes, competition with the rival Social Service Employees Union, and the eventual merger of the two as the SSEU Local 371. Union materials include those documenting committee and chapter activities, negotiations, and recruitment. Gorelick was also active in professional organizations and advocacy groups, including the National Association of Social Workers and the Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Lung Association. Documents from these organizations and others illustrate how a social worker's activism could span work, union, volunteer, and professional activities.
Gorelick, Sol, 1916-2004
Historical/Biographical Note
Sol Gorelick (1916-2004) was a social worker and union activist. He began his career with the City of New York in 1940 as a caseworker at the Brownsville Welfare Center. After an absence to serve in World War II, Gorelick returned to the Department of Welfare. He would work with the department and its successor, the Human Resources Administration, until his retirement in 1980. Gorelick worked at several welfare (also termed income maintenance) centers in Brooklyn including the Boro Hall Center and the Fulton Center, for which he was director.
Gorelick joined the United Public Workers union when he started with the city. Following the UPW's dissolution amid the CIO's anti-Communist purges, Gorelick would join the Welfare Local 371 (later the Social Service Employees Union Local 371) of AFSCME, District Council 37. During the 1960s Gorelick served as a vice president of DC 37.
Gorelick was also active in many other profession organizations and advocacy groups, including the National Association of Social Workers and the Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Lung Association.
Scope and Contents note
These papers document the career, labor activities, and activism of Sol Gorelick.
The largest series is comprised of documents from government entities concerned with social welfare. Most come from Gorelick's employer, the New York City Department of Human Resources, and its predecessors. These materials document the procedures and results of the city's welfare programs. The city's bureaucratic culture profoundly impacted its relationship with its employees and welfare clients. The resulting body of directives, memorandums, and correspondence show all facets of this experience. Because of welfare's relationship with other areas, the collection also illustrates unemployment, crime, and housing conditions in mid-20th century Brooklyn, with Brownsville being particularly well-represented.
Gorelick was a member of Social Service Employees Union, Local 371, which represented employees in the City of New York's welfare departments. A significant portion of the collection documents this local, its predecessor unions, and its parent union, AFSCME, District Council 37.
The collection also gives insight into trends in the profession of social work, and shows how an individual's activism could span work, union activities, and professional organization participation.
Related Archival Materials
Social Service Employees Union Records (WAG 003)
AFSCME, District Council 37 Records (WAG 265)
The Verne Weed Collection for Progressive Social Work records at the University of Minnesota's Social Welfare History Archives also holds papers of Sol Gorelick.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series: City, State, Federal Social Welfare Programs; Labor and Unions; National Association of Social Workers; and Organizations and Subjects.
Files within each series are arranged alphabetically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Materials found in repository; provenance is unknown but were likely donated by Sol Gorelick in the late 1980s. The accession number associated with these materials is 1950.268.
Access Restrictions
The majority of the collection is open for research without restrictions. Restricted folders are noted in the finding aid. These materials include files with personal information on individuals' welfare cases and employee files. Please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu for more information.
AFSCME. District Council 37 (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Lung Association.; National Association of Social Workers.; New York City Human Resources Administration.; Social Service Employees Union. Local 371.; Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Collective labor agreements |x Social workers.; Income maintenance programs; Social case work; Social workers; Unemployment |z New York (State) |z New York; White collar workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
- City, State, and Federal Social Welfare Programs, 1
  Historical/Biographical Note
  Sol Gorelick began his career with the City of New York in 1940 at the Brownsville Welfare Center and retired in 1980. During this time, the city's departments concerned with welfare (also termed income maintenance) and social services saw many reorganizations and policy changes based on the city's social conditions, forces within the government, and trends in the field of social work.
  Consistent with national trends, New York City's government welfare programs were solidified as a result of the New Deal programs of the Great Depression. The 1935 Social Security Act included funds for unemployment and the Aid to Dependent Children program (later Aid to Families With Dependent Children). Funding came from the federal government and states. States and local governments administered the program.
  By the 1940s, the Department of Welfare was one of many New York City government entities providing social services. In 1966, a merger of various social welfare agencies created the Human Resources Administration. While the Department of Welfare was included in the merger, its commissioner retained some autonomy from the Human Resources Administration until the positions of commissioner and administrator of the Human Resources Administration were finally merged in 1970.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains materials from Gorelick's tenure with the City of New York. It primarily consists of City of New York documents, but also contains information and instructions from state and federal social welfare departments. The series contains materials from the 1940s-1980s, but the bulk are from the 1960s-1970s.
  The City of New York was an extremely bureaucratic entity, an attribute that fundamentally shaped its labor relations with social service employees and the relationship between welfare clients and city employees. The memorandums, directives, and correspondence found here illustrate working conditions of social service employees and processes for administering welfare (also termed income maintenance). Because the need for welfare was connected with many other social issues, these records illustrate social conditions in mid-20th century New York City, including poverty, health, housing, employment, and crime.
  The Fulton Center, on Willoughby Street in Brooklyn, and the Boro Hall Center on Jay Street in Brooklyn are particularly well-represented. Gorelick held several positions at Boro Hall and was director at Fulton during the 1970s. The Brownsville Center is also represented to a lesser extent. These local centers were where clients interacted with the city's policies.
  Departments are arranged alphabetically, but due to the evolution of the city government, similar functions are represented by content generated by different departments. The functions of the Department of Welfare would gradually be moved into the Department of Human Resources Administration/Department of Social Services, which was created in 1966 and fully consolidated in 1970. The local centers, such as Fulton, Boro Hall, or Brownsville, were at times under the auspices of the Department of Welfare, the Department of Social Services, or the Human Resources Administration.
  Advocacy and professional organizations for government employees are also included in this series. These include the Department of Welfare's branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and the Association of Supervisor's of the Department of Welfare. This group, formed "to advance professional growth and to protect the Civil Service rights of members," illustrates the often fine line between professional organization and union activities.
  - Advisory Council on Public Welfare (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Plan for Community Social Services, East New York, Human Resources District # 13 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Association of Jewish Employees (Department of Welfare) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Association of Supervisors of the Department of Welfare (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Association of Supervisors of the Department of Welfare - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Association of Supervisors of the Department of Welfare - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Association of Supervisors of the Department of Welfare - Correspondence (recieved) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Association of Supervisors of the Department of Welfare - Membership Committee (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Association of Supervisors of the Department of Welfare - Salary Appeals (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Association of Supervisors of the Deparment of Welfare - Seminar on Administration (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Assaults on Staff - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Audit of Implementation of Title IVA/IVD (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
  - Bay Ridge Center Complaint - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Board of Education (New York City) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board of Estimate - General Pay Plan Regulations (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Boro Hall Center (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Boro Hall Center - Administrative Assistants - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Boro Hall Center - Administrators and Case Supervisors Meeting (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Boro Hall Center - Allowance Schedules (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Boro Hall Center - Assaults (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Boro Hall Center - Assaults - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Boro Hall Center- Bureau of Child Welfare Consultant - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Boro Hall Center - Cases - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Boro Hall Center - Case Aide Training Program (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Boro Hall Center - Case Correspondence - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Boro Hall Center - Case Lists - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Boro Hall Center - Case Reviews - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Boro Hall Center - Case Statistics - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Boro Hall Center - Case Supervisors - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Boro Hall Center - Case Supervisors Conference - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Boro Hall Center - Correspondence with Bureau of Child Welfare (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Boro Hall Center - Correspondence with Universities (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Boro Hall Center - Educational Needs (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Boro Hall Center - Emergency Personnel Directory (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Boro Hall Center - Employment (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Boro Hall Center - Extradepartmental Facilities (Clinics, Hospitals, Daycare, etc.) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Boro Hall Center - Fair Hearings - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Boro Hall Center - Fire and Disaster Coverage - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Boro Hall Center - Guide to Frequently-used Forms (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Boro Hall Center - Housing - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Boro Hall Center - Medicaid (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Boro Hall Center - Neglected Child Referrals - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Boro Hall Center - "Our Difficulties, Our Problems" (Conflict between career staff members and SSEU staff) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Boro Hall Center - Personnel Problems - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Boro Hall Center - Procedural Memos (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Boro Hall Center - Psychiatric Program - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Boro Hall Center - Quarterly Reports (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Boro Hall Center - Salary Classification Appeals - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Boro Hall Center - Staff - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Boro Hall Center - Summary of Welfare Benefit Plans (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Boro Hall Center - Territory Guide (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Boro Hall - Training Materials (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Boro Hall Center - Training Materials - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 21-22)
  - Boro Hall Center - Utilities for Public Assistance Recipients - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - Bronx Income Maintenance Centers (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Brownsville Center (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Brownsville Center - Brownsville Brotherhood Committee (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
  - Brownsville Center - Field staff training (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Brownsville GSS Advisory Council - Title XX Budget Plan (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brownsville Center - Unit Clerk (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bureau of Labor Statistics Report on NYC (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bureau of Personnel - Recruitment Program (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bureau of Public Assistance (New York City) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bureau of Public Assistance (New York City) - Case Supervisors Training Program (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bureau of Public Assistance - Interviewing for Staff Selection in Public Welfare Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bureau of Public Assistance - Thank You Card "memo" from Vincent Porteus (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bushwick Model Center (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - CALS Committee (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Career and Salary Board of Appeals (New York City) - (includes brief by Local 371) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Career and Salary Board of Appeals (New York City) - Salary Allocations in Civil Service Occupations (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Center Directors Advisory Committee (Box 2, Folder 13-22)
  - Center Directors Advisory Committee (Includes Chicago Report) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Center Directors Advisory Committee - General Meeting (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Center Directors Advisory Committee - Training Committee (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Citizens Advisory Committee - Welfare Advocacy Training Program (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - City Planning Commission (New York City) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - City Planning Commission (New York City) - Gorelick Testimony (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Community Agency/Organization Interactions (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Community Social Services Manual (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA) Information (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence with Universities (Field Instruction) - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 24)
  - The Council of the City of New York (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Crown Heights District Service Council (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Department of Civil Service (New York State) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Department of Civil Service (New York State) - Job Specifications for Social Workers (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Department of Civil Service (New York State) - Manual of Procedure in Disciplinary Action (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Department of Health - Community Service Program (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Department of Health, Education and Welfare (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Department of Health, Employment and Welfare - Draft of Secretary's Statement for New York Press Conference (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Department of Income Maintenance (Human Resources Administration) - Management Plan (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Department of Income Management, Division of Location and Support - Policies and Forms (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Department of Personnel (New York City) (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Department of Personnel (New York City) - Proposed Personnel Order 78/9 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Department of Personnel (New York City) and AFSCME, District Council 37 - Form DP-325A (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Department of Relocation (New York City) - Relocation News (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) (Box 3, Folder 2-7)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 25-29)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Ad Hoc Committee on Safety (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Application for Reduced-tuition Evening Classes (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Child Welfare Training (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Community Advisory and Policy Group (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Forms (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Intradepartmental Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - McMillan Library (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Office of Case Intake and Management (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Office of Training, Institute for Community Organization Consultants (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Office of Training, "Orientation Program for Supervisors I" (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Policy Recommendations (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Rebudgeting (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Separation of Income Maintenance and Service Operations (Box 3, Folder 21-23)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Statistical Reports (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Department of Social Services (New York City) - Summer Urban Corps Summary (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Department of Social Services (New York State) (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Department of Social Services (New York State) - Regional Community Services Forum Report (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Department of Social Welfare (New York State) - Categorical Pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) (Box 3, Folder 29-36)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Employment Program Training (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Functional Organization Chart (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Information on Organizing and Grievances (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Manual for the Custodial Force (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Office of Training Quarterly Report (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Personnel Manual (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Procedural Outline for Employment (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Procedural Outline for Housing (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Procedures (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Social Audit (Procedures and Forms) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Staff Development News (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Telephone System and Directory (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Territory Guides (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Testimony of Mitchell I. Grinsberg Before Senate Subcommittee on Employment, Manpower, and Poverty (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - "Three Month Curriculum for New Case Workers" (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Training and Employment for Mothers in Part-time Occupations (TEMPO) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Department of Welfare (New York City) - Welfare Locations (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Employee Blood Program (New York City) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Employees Retirement System (New York City) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Executive Department, Division of the Budget (New York State) - Grant for Public Assistance Recipients (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Executive Order 10988 - The White House (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Experimental Welfare Center Project - Progress Report (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Federal Corrupt Practices and Political Activities Legislation (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Federal Survey - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 30)
  - Final Title IV/XVI Social Services Regulations (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Fort Greene Social Services Center - Complaint Regarding Functioning of Income Maintenance Unit (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - 4201 Schools for the Deaf and Blind - Teacher Salaries (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Fulton Center (Box 4, Folder 22-30)
  - Fulton Center - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 31-32)
  - Fulton Center - "A Typical Day of a Center Director" by Simon Miller (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Fulton Center - Administrative Staff Meeting (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Fulton Center - Bomb Threat (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Fulton Center - Building (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Fulton Center - Cases - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 33)
  - Fulton Center - Case Lists - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 34)
  - Fulton Center - Case Statistics (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Fulton Center - Community Relations (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Fulton Center - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
  - Fulton Center - Correspondence with Bureau of Public Assistance Director (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Fulton Center - Correspondence with Citizens' Committee for Children (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Fulton Center - Correspondence with Bureau of Public Assistance Director - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 35)
  - Fulton Center - Criteria for Managerial Evaluation (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Fulton Center - Error Accountability Report (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Fulton Center - Error Rate Audit (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Fulton Center - Extradepartmental Facilities: Treatment, Residential, Etc. (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Fulton Center - Face to Face Recertification Program Pilot (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Fulton Center - Field Managers Meetings (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Fulton Center - Food Stamps (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Fulton Center - Grace Hotel Squatters - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 36)
  - Fulton Center - Housing Committee (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Fulton Center - Income Maintenance Backlogging (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Fulton Center - Income Maintenance for Striking Union Members (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Fulton Center - Location Chart (Directory) (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Fulton Center - Managerial Position Description (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Fulton Center - Meeting with East New York Community Corporation (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Fulton Center - Memos to Staff (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Fulton Center - Patrol Force (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Fulton Center - Performance of Police Force (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Fulton Center - Planned Parenthood (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Fulton Center - Procedural Memos (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Fulton Center - Procedural Memos (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fulton Center - Quarterly Reports (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fulton Center - Special Tasks and Administrative Assistant Duties (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Fulton Center - Staff - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 37)
  - Fulton Center - Staff Assignments - RESTRICTED (Box 17, Folder 38)
  - Fulton Center - Staff Committee (Black and Puerto Rican Celebration) (Box 5, Folder 4)